Guide to the Alfred White Van Sinderen Collection of Charles Babbage
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Alfred White Van Sinderen collection of Charles Babbage
1810-1990
1820-1864
GEN MSS 1362
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.63
(2 boxes)
Correspondence of Charles Babbage, writings by Babbage, and other related papers collected by Alfred White Van Sinderen. Correspondence, circa 1810-1864 and undated, consists of autograph letters, signed, most from Babbage to colleagues, friends, and others; also present are a few letters to Babbage and third party letters. Correspondents include Alexander Dallas Bache; Michael Faraday; William Henry Fitton; Benjamin Hawes; Ada King, Countess of Lovelace; and Peter Mark Roget. Writings by Babbage include a untitled poem, autograph manuscript, circa 1817-1820, about Babbage's unsuccessful efforts to obtain an academic appointment; "To the Electors of Finsbury," 1832 November 12, printed proof, about Babbage's views during the Parliamentary election; and an autograph manuscript account book, 1810-1827. Most correspondence and writings are accompanied by typed transcripts and notes made by Van Sinderen. Other papers include additional notes by Van Sinderen and vendor descriptions for books by Babbage.
Van Sinderen, Alfred White, 1924-1998
Babbage, Charles, 1791-1871
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alfred White Van Sinderen (Yale 1945), 1991 and 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Charles Babbage (1791-1871)
British mathematician and computer pioneer.
Alfred White Van Sinderen (1924-1998) (Yale 1945)
Southern New England Telecommunications Corporation executive, 1947-1985; faculty fellow, Yale University School of Organization and Management; and Yale University Library Associates trustee. Van Sinderen assembled his collection of books and manuscripts relating to Charles Babbage during the 1960s through 1990s.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence of Charles Babbage, writings by Babbage, and other related papers collected by Alfred White Van Sinderen. Correspondence, circa 1810-1864 and undated, consists of autograph letters, signed, most from Babbage to colleagues, friends, and others; also present are a few letters to Babbage and third party letters. Correspondents include Alexander Dallas Bache; Michael Faraday; William Henry Fitton; Benjamin Hawes; Ada King, Countess of Lovelace; and Peter Mark Roget. Writings by Babbage include a untitled poem, autograph manuscript, circa 1817-1820, about Babbage's unsuccessful efforts to obtain an academic appointment; "To the Electors of Finsbury," 1832 November 12, printed proof, about Babbage's views during the Parliamentary election; and an autograph manuscript account book, 1810-1827. Most correspondence and writings are accompanied by typed transcripts and notes by Van Sinderen. Other papers include additional notes made by Van Sinderen and vendor descriptions for books by Babbage.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence of Charles Babbage, 1810-1864. II. Writings of Charles Babbage, 1810-1832. III. Other Papers, 1700s-1990s.
Computer scientists -- Great Britain; Scientists -- Great Britain; Finsbury (London, England) -- Politics and government -- 19th century; Account books -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Scientists -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Babbage, Charles, 1791-1871; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867; Faraday, Michael, 1791-1867; Fitton, William Henry, 1780-1861; Hawes, B. (Benjamin), 1797-1862; Lovelace, Ada King, Countess of, 1815-1852; Roget, Peter Mark, 1779-1869; Van Sinderen, Alfred White, 1924-1998
- Correspondence of Charles Babbage, 1810 - 1864; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Letters are from Babbage, unless otherwise noted in file title.
  - "Adolphus, John, Mrs.", 1859 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Babbage, Benjamin Herschel, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), (1806-1867), 1837 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), (1806-1867), 1854 August 8 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Barlow, Peter (1776-1862), 1843, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bell, Marion Snow, [1854] May 13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Booth, Mr.", 1827 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brewster, David (1781-1868), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brookfield, William Henry (1809-1874), 1854 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Buckingham and Chandos, Richard Temple Nugent Brydges Chandos, Duke of (1776-1839), [1830] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Burdett-Coutts, Angela Georgina, 1863 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Colby, Colonel", 1836 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Crosse, Mrs.", 1863 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Denman, Theodosia Vevers, 1840 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dollond, George (1774-1852), [1830 June 1] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Drummond, Thomas, Mrs.", 1843 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Faraday, Michael (1791-1867), 1828, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fitton, William Henry (1780-1861), 1824-1832 July (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Fitton, William Henry (1780-1861), 1832 September-1838 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Fitton, William Henry (1780-1861) (transcripts only), 1827, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Fox, Mary, Lady, 1836, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Gazzieri, Professor", 1846 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Gilbert, Davies (1767-1839), 1823 June 16-28 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Gravatt, William (1806-1866), 1858 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Greathead, Percy, [1822 August] (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Gregory, Duncan Farquharson (1813-1844), 1840 June 13 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Grove, Mrs.", 1861 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Hall, Lady", 1853 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Hallam, Miss", 1841 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Harris, W. Snow (William Snow), Sir (1791-1867), 1834 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Hawes, B. (Benjamin), (1797-1862), 1837-1858 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "Herries, Lady", undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William) (1792-1871), 1821 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William) (1792-1871) (to Babbage), [1829 June?] (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Hollier, Sophy, 1859, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Hooker, William Jackson, Sir (1785-1865), 1857 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "Horner, Mrs.", undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Institution of Civil Engineers (Great Britain), 1856 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Isaac, Harriet Whitmore, 1829 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "James, Miss", undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Kinglake, Alexander William (1809-1891), 1854 July 9 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - "Kinglake, Miss", [1862 or 1863?] (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Lemon, Charles, Sir (1784-1868), 1836 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Lovelace, Ada King, Countess of (1815-1852), 1846 June 31 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Lovelace, Ada King, Countess of (1815-1852) (to Babbage), [1842?] November 6 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - [Martin, Robert Montgomery (1803?-1868)?], 1857 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Merivale, Herman (1806-1874), undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - "Milman, Mrs.", 1841 March 15 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Monk, James Henry (1784-1856), [early 1840s] (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir (1792-1871), undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Owen, Richard (1804-1892), 1853 August 18 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Porter, G. R., 1840 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - "Powell, Mr.", 1831 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - "Robinson, Mrs.", 1860 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Roget, Peter Mark (1779-1869), 1819-1824, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - "Rose, H., Professor", 1835 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Royal Society (Great Britain), 1830 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Ryan, Edward (1793-1875), 1852 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Senior, Nassau William (1790-1864), 1852 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Sharp, Richard (1759-1835), [early 1830s] February 5 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Sharpey, William (1802-1880), 1859 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Smythe, Warrington, 1864 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Statistical Society (Great Britain), 1863 February 18-20 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Stepney, Catherine Pollock Manners, Lady (-1845), 1840 July 14 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Timbs, John (1801-1875), 1858 November 29 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Tooke, William (1777-1863), 1827 January 28 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Wellington, Arthur Wellesley, Duke of (1769-1852) (to Babbage), 1849 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Wheatstone, Charles, Sir (1802-1875), 1838, undated (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Unidentified, 1810-1843 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Unidentified, 1843-1860s, undated (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Writings of Charles Babbage, 1810-1832; Series II
  - Account book, 1810-1827 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Note about "tit-tat-too" game, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Poem, [circa 1817-1820] (Box 2, Folder 73)
    First line: "Sir Alphabet Function a knight much renown'd"
  - "To the Electors of Finsbury", 1832 November 12 (Box 2, Folder 74)
- Other Papers, 1700s-1990s; Series III
  Most materials removed from books relating to Babbage owned by Van Sinderen
  - Babbage, Henry Provost. Letter to an unidentified recipient, 1917 October 12 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Portrait of Joseph-Marie Jacquard (woven on silk), undated (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Unidentified manuscripts, [18th-19th century] (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Vendor descriptions, [circa 1970s-1990s] (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Other notes and printed material, 1936-1995, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)